<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some queries propounded to the Common-Councell, and citizens of London, concerning the armies demand of having the militia of London of the 4th of May changed. Wherein the unreasonablenesse and great danger of that proposall, and the justifiablenesse of the cities refusall both in law and conscience, are fully demonstrated.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4561A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E400_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862257</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862257</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114410</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114410)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E400[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some queries propounded to the Common-Councell, and citizens of London, concerning the armies demand of having the militia of London of the 4th of May changed. Wherein the unreasonablenesse and great danger of that proposall, and the justifiablenesse of the cities refusall both in law and conscience, are fully demonstrated.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114410:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME QUERIES Propounded to the <hi>Common-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> and Citizens of LONDON, concerning the <hi>Armies</hi> Demand of having the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London</hi> of the 4th. of <hi>May</hi> changed.</p>
            <p>Wherein the unreaſonableneſſe and great danger of that Propoſall, and the Juſtifiableneſſe of the Cities refuſall both in Law and Conſcience, are fully demonſtrated.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 13. 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Now there was no Smith found throughout all the land of Iſrael: (for the Philiſtines ſaid, Leſt the Hebrews make them ſwords or ſpeares)</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>20</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But all the Iſraelites went down to the Philiſtines, to ſharpen every man his ſhare, and his coulter, and his ax, and his mattock.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>22</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>So it came to paſſe in the day of battell, that there was neither ſword nor ſpear found in the hand of any of the people that were with Saul and Jonathan.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 King. 21. 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And Naboth ſaid to Ahab, The Lord forbid it me, that I ſhould give the INHERITANCE OF MY FATHERS VNTO THEE.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 King. 2. 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And why doeſt thou ask Abiſhag the Shunammite for Adonijah? ASK FOR HIM THE KINGDOM ALSO.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 30. 21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For three things the earth is diſquieted, and for four which it cannot bear:</p>
               <p>For a SERVANT when he reigneth, and a FOOL when he is filled.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nulli deterius dominantur quam ſervi.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Yeer 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb facs="tcp:114410:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114410:2"/>
            <p>O Fooliſh Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> who hath bewitched you? what ſpirit of madneſſe hath poſſeſſed you, that you ſhould beleeve any of the lying and fained words of the Army, and not ſee ſlavery and deſtruction coming upon your ſelves, and poſteritie, as travail upon a woman with childe, which you cannot eſcape, if once you give up your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiae</hi> upon the Demand of the Army? O <hi>London, London,</hi> thou haſt befooled thy ſelf already almoſt irrecoverably by thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances and Treaties with the Army, by thy interpoſing for the Army with the Parliament to grant ſeverall things: as that all Liſtings might be forborn, that the Reformadoes might be put out of the Line of Communication, with divens other things, whereby that wicked party in the Army that rules all, <hi>Cromwell</hi> and his Fellows have forced by their threatnings the 11. Members to withdraw from the Houſe, many others to go to their own homes, and ſo all things whatſoever are carried according to the will and pleaſure of that Sectarian faction in the Army, and in the Houſe of Commons, both joyned together to deſtroy Religion, Laws, Liberties, and to enſlave this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by bringing it into the condition of the <hi>Turkiſh Empire,</hi> to rule all at pleaſure by an Army, <hi>Cromwell</hi> being turned <hi>Turke,</hi> the Sectarian faction muſt be as the <hi>Janizaries</hi> to uphold him. The ſtrange, daily and endleſſe Propoſals from the Army of having all the Forces of the Kingdom in the hand of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> of having all the Laws of the Land concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion taken away, of releaſing <hi>Lilburne, Overton</hi> out of priſon, and all perſons whatſoever for matters of conſcience (unleſſe proved Papiſts) though Antiſcripturiſts, Antitrinitarians, Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, with the demand of changing the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> are clear and evident proofs of full intentions to deſtroy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Liberty, Property; and to rule all by the Sword and a Councell of War.</p>
            <p>O <hi>London, London,</hi> would to God thou kneweſt even <hi>at leaſt in this thy day the things whïch belong unto thy peace:</hi> Behold now is the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114410:3"/>accepted time, behold now is the day of ſalvation, preſerve thy <hi>Militia</hi> from being changed, &amp; ſhew thy ſelf this once to ſtand upon thy rights and liberties, and thou mayeſt yet break the neck of all the curſed deſignes on foot, and be the Saviour of the King, Parliament and Kingdom, and ſhall be called, <hi>The Repaiter of the breach, the Reſtorer of paths to dwell in.</hi> But ſuffer thy <hi>Militia</hi> to be thus taken away, and now altogether hold thy peace, ſitting down and looſing the preſent opportunitie, and thou art loſt for even according to humane help; and thou ſhalt find that verified of thee, <hi>Time was, Time is, Time is paſt;</hi> and thou ſhalt repent when 'tis too late. And, O thou <hi>London,</hi> and thou Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to make you ſenſible, and to ſtir in time, know aſſuredly the work now on foot by chief Agents in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and ſome of the Houſe of Commons, is not of yeſterday, nor a buſineſſe of not disbanding till full Arrears, and an Act of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnity for the Souldiery (however theſe have been held out as pretences, and made uſe of to draw the Souldiery in, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie on their deſignes long before layed) but 'tis a Deſigne and Plot that hath been layed theſe foure yeers laſt paſt, by force of Arms,<note place="margin">☞</note> an Army of the Sectaries modelling, to bring into this Kingdom a Generall Toleration of all Religions, to deſtroy the Civill Government in the fundamentall conſtitution of King, Lords and Commons, and to bring King <hi>Charles</hi> to Juſtice (ſo they call it) as the grand Delinquent in all the three Kingdoms; the Common Law and Statutes of this Kingdom, the Miniſtery, the Reformed Churches, to poſſeſſe themſelves of, and be Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the City of <hi>London,</hi> to get to themſelves and their party all the eſtates, riches, and great places of the Kingdom, and to rule all by an Arbitrary new modelled Government of their own ſetting up, and by a perpetuall Army: for the full Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of which, beſides that their daily actions and Propoſals of getting all Power into their hands ſpeak as much; there are two Books already Printed called, <hi>The totall and finall Demands of the Army,</hi> and <hi>Works of Darkneſſe brought to light,</hi> that give a great deal of light in divers of theſe particulars: and there are two other Diſcourſes ready for the Preſſe, written by Authors that have obſerved and layed all things together both in the Army and the Houſe of Commons by that Partie, that will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114410:3"/>more fully prove every part of this Deſigne, by laying down all the Preparations to it, and all the Proceedings in it; and how there is nothing wanting to the perfecting and compleating of it, but to have the full power upon the City of <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> and the Navy in their hands. Onely in the interim till thoſe Gentlemens Books can be Printed, I will give two or three proofes of the Deſigne of the Sectarian Partie to bring the King to Juſtice (as they phraſe it) and to take off his head.</p>
            <p>To ſay nothing of the many ſpeeches ſpoken by ſome of that Party both in the Army, Houſe of Commons, and City of brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the King to Juſtice, nor of the many wicked paſſages printed to that purpoſe: I will onely relate three paſſages that have come lately to my knowledge. The firſt, that preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King was ſeized on by the Army, two perſons here in <hi>London,</hi> one a great Agent of <hi>Cromwels,</hi> and very intimate wich him; the other a great Agent of <hi>Rainsboroughs,</hi> told an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Citizen, that the Deſigne of taking the King, was not to joyn with him againſt the Parliament (however they held fair with the King and his Party) but to bring him to Juſtice; for if he ever came in again, and had any Power,<note place="margin">☜</note> there were ſo many of the malignant partie in the Houſe of Commons, that they joyning with him, no honeſt man ſhould keep his head on his ſhoulders; and without this, neither ſuch as belonged to this Army, nor any others could be ſecured. Secondly, ſince the Army have gotten the King, divers of their partie, Members of the Houſe of Commons the Kings moſt mortall Enemies, have, been with one Mr. <hi>Willingam,</hi> who keeps all the writings of <hi>Windebanks,</hi> and other Papers of State, to look out, and peruſe them for that end, to ſee what matter they might finde againſt the King to make a Charge of; and this Mr. <hi>Willingham</hi> hath been ſent to, and written unto by the Army about theſe Papers, and to come down to the Army. Thirdly, Mr. <hi>Marſhall</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nye</hi> coming from the Army (too good friends to <hi>Cromwell</hi> and that party) ſaid to divers Members of the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> asking them about the Armies Propoſitions, that the King ſhould never have any Power more, the Army would look to that: he ſhould for his own Family, and in his Chappell, enjoy the liberty of his Conſcience, but have never more to do in the Government of the Kingdom.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114410:4"/>
            <p>And I would ask any reaſonable man, ſeeing they have agreed and declared thus much already, that the King ſhall have no more power, how long time he thinks when they have gotten all the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> into their hands, and have new mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled the Houſe of Commons, as they have done the Army, he ſhall enjoy his Conſcience, or his life?</p>
            <p>And therefore, O Common Councell, and Citizens of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and all who love the King and his Poſterity, the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, the Priviledges of Parliament, the Reformed Proteſtant Religion, part not with your <hi>Militia,</hi> give not ſuch a Sword into the hands of bruitiſh unreaſonable men, to deſtroy your ſelves, and all thats dear to you with; And that you may lawfully, and with a good conſcience keep your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> for the yeer, and that to part with it at the pleaſure of the Army, is very unſafe, and moſt dangerous: I deſire theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>Quaeries</hi> may be well conſidered of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether an Ordinance made by Parliament in a time (unqueſtionably) of Freedom and liberty, and in full Houſes, upon mature deliberation, and after many dayes debate, after anſwering all objections againſt the perſons and things, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſcanning upon every particular perſon contained in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and this done upon the deſire of the City to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and their nomination choice of the perſons to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Parliament, be to be judged more valid binding, or an Ordinance made after Members driven away by the threats and approaches of an Army, and upon the Demand of an Army, and in a thin Houſe of Commons, and concluded upon on a ſudden?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whether or no, if the Parliament by Ordinance after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture adviſe and deliberation in full Parliament had given the City of <hi>London</hi> towards the payment of their debts, five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand pounds, and thereupon the City had been in poſſeſſion of the money, in caſe the Parliament upon another Ordinance made upon the deſire of the Army, after threatnings and driving away Members, ſhould have revoked this money, whether would the City hold themſelves bound in Law or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to part with it? and if not, as I ſuppoſe, they would not. Then, I conceive, they are leſſe bound to part with their <hi>Militia</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114410:4"/>as being much more to them; without which, they can neither keep their Eſtates, lives or liberties, but all they have, as the caſe ſtands, is expoſed to ruine.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Whether it would not have been judged, and cried out of in the King, as great injuſtice, breach of the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, &amp;c. when he had given the grant of any thing for life, or for term of yeers under the great Seal, he ſhould upon his own will, without any fault in the perſons, have taken it from them before half the time expired? And if it would be ſo in the King, what is it in the Parliament to recall the <hi>Militia</hi> before half the time be out?</p>
            <p n="4">4. What is any Ordinance of Parliament worth, or will be accounted of by any, if as ſoon as tis granted, it may be thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called? And upon what a ſlender foundation, or broken reed, will not men ſay they have built on all this while, in lending thoſe vaſt ſummes of money to the State, and in acting for the Parliament, if Ordinances by the Parliament it ſelf be ſo eaſily made void, and broken? will ever men venture their lives and eſtates upon Ordinances?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether the Armies deſire of having the <hi>Militia</hi> thus changed, and putting the Parliament ſo upon it, to take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way againſt the will of the Common Councell, and perſons en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, without any reaſon at all given, or unfaithfulneſſe found in them, be not to put the Parliament upon exerciſing a meer Arbitrary Power, and to rule by will, and ſo againſt the Common Rights and liberty of the Subject, ſo much complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by the Army in all their Repreſentations, Remonſtrances, Declarations, Letters, and made the ground of their refuſing to disband, and of all the late differences between them and the Parliament?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether in the judgement of any indifferent men, it can ſtand with the honour, Juſtice, Authority, and Gravity of the ſupreme Court of Judicature, and the great Councell of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, when upon mature deliberation, and weightie reaſons in the moſt legall way, and with the beſt ſecuritie they have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a thing to perſons highly deſerving of them, and of known fidelity to them, and the publick, to take it away of a ſudden without giving any reaſon at all, or indeed there being any juſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114410:5"/>cauſe for ſo doing, but rather much to the contrary?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether or no, according to the judgement of the beſt Reformed Divines, both forrain and Engliſh, 'tis not held law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Subjects, when by their Princes a Power is given unto them of Cities, Forts, Caſtles, and Militia, for their ſafety and ſecurity againſt an oppoſite party in the Land that would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, to hold and keep them for their defence againſt Edicts and Commands of Princes requiring to give them up; yea againſt Armies ſent to take them away by force? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Divines who allow of any Defenſive Arms in any Caſes to Subjects, yea,<note n="*" place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Abbot, De Antichriſto,</hi> and eſpecially Bp. <hi>Morton</hi> in his Sermon preached in the North, before the K. of ſubjection to the higher Powers, and againſt reſiſting. Authority even then when the King went againſt the Scots, how he excepts that Caſe of keeping Forts, Militia, given on purpoſe for ſecurity, which I conceive he did on purpoſe according to the judgement of other Proteſtant Divines, to free the Proteſtants in France, and the Rochellers from R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bellion, in ſtanding upon their own defence in thoſe Towns and Cities given them for their ſecurity againſt the bloody Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</note> Biſhops the moſt tender of Subjects diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Commands of Princes, or of taking up Arms, do not in that controverſie of Defenſive Arms, grant it lawfull in this caſe of having Forts, Caſtles, Militia given them for defence, to keep them, as the Proteſtants of <hi>France</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Rochel;</hi> and if this be ſo, whether is it not much more lawfull for the City to keep their <hi>Militia</hi> now for the time according to the grant of Parliament?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Whether or no, many learned Divines beyond the Seas, as <hi>Pareus,</hi> &amp;c. who are for Subjects Defenſive Arms; and others at home, as Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Beadles,</hi> Doctor <hi>Willet,</hi> &amp;c. though they hold it unlawfull for private perſons who are not Magiſtrates, nor have no part in the Civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to take up Arms againſt the higher Powers; do they not hold it lawfull, in ſome caſes, after Petitioning, and uſing all other means and remedies, for inferiour Magiſtrates the next in Power and Intereſt to the Supreme, to take up Arms to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves and the People in their rights againſt certain ruine; which if it be ſo, then certainly the Magiſtracie of the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Lord Mayor, and Court of Common Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell being the greateſt Power next the King, and both Houſes of Parliament, and having, next the King and the Houſes, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114410:5"/>greateſt Intereſt in the Kingdom; and being the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part of any City or County in the Kingdom, for the ſafetie of the whole may lawfully when the King is ſeiſed on by an Army, and kept againſt his will, the Parliament over-awed, and the whole Kingdom in danger of ruine, keep the Power of the <hi>Militia</hi> ſetled upon them in their hands, for the preſerving of the King, Parliament, themſelves, and the Kingdom?</p>
            <p n="9">9. Whether or no, if a Father, Maſter, or a Friend ſhould give his ſon, ſervant, or friend a ſword into either of their hands to defend Father and himſelf, if another ſervant ſhould come with a ſword to the Maſter, and by holding the ſword over him, and by threats work him to command the other to lay down his ſword, and to give it to him whereby either to kill both Maſter and ſervant; or elſe to put upon them what conditions he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: may not the ſon, or the ſervant in ſuch a caſe lawfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſuch a command, and keep the ſword both to preſerve his own life, and his Fathers? And if ſo, whether this be not the caſe now of the Armies demanding of the Parliament the Sword they gave to the City; and of the Cities humble deſire to keep it for the ſafetie of Parliament and themſelves?</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whether if that this Power of the Cities chooſing and having their <hi>Militia</hi> in their own hands, being one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions upon long and mature deliberation paſſed by both Houſes, and agreed on by the Commiſſioners of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be preſented to the King to be confirmed, ſhould be thus taken away by the Parliament preſently after paſſed by an Ordinance; may it not give an occaſion and ground to the King to break this and other Propoſitions after ſigning them, ſaying, the Parliament more engaged to the City for their adhering to them, then I was to the Parliament or City, broke with the City, and that in the principall the <hi>Militia:</hi> and and why may not I then break with the City?</p>
            <p n="11">11. Whether or no may not the City of <hi>London</hi> juſtly alledge for their keeping the <hi>Militia,</hi> and not giving it up upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Army, a true reall neceſſity of ſelf preſervation; and not onely a pretended neceſſity as the Army did for not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding, as alſo the liberty and freedom of the Subject, the ſolemn League and Covenant for Reformation, &amp;c. which the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114410:6"/>Army in all their Remonſtrances, Declarations, &amp;c. never ſo much as once took notice of, or ſo much as pretended, as indeed intending to deſtroy it, and revoke it; as appears by their laſt Propoſall, of revoking all the penall Statutes for matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and full freedome for all private meetings for religious Exerciſes.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Whether the City of <hi>London</hi> in their humble refuſall of giving up their <hi>Militia</hi> in this juncture of time to the will of the Army, do not perform an high act of faithfulneſſe to His Majeſties Perſon Crown, and Poſterity? And whether the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering it up were not putting a ſword into the hands of mad men, to deſtroy the King and his Poſteritie with?</p>
            <p n="13">13. Whether if the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhould part with their <hi>Militia</hi> at this time, they do not, in as much as in them lyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray, and give up Religion, the King, and his Poſterity, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Laws, liberties, the whole Kingdom, yea the three Kingdoms to the wills, luſts, and Revelations of an unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, bruitiſh, Anabaptiſticall Army? And are they not guilty of fearfull breach of Covenant, and of putting a ſword into ſuch hands to deſtroy all with?</p>
            <p n="14">14. Whether or no, conſidering all the Demands hitherto of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Army under his (I would ſay <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi>) Command, as to have the command of all Forces, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, &amp;c. in <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> as to have all Statutes for Religion repealed, &amp;c. and in this now of asking for the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> may it not be ſaid as <hi>Solomon</hi> of <hi>Adonijah,</hi> And why does Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> ask the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> let him <hi>ask the Kingdom alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. Whether or no, ſo ſoon as the City ſhall have parted with their <hi>Militia</hi> according to the deſire of the Army, and the Armies Deputies <hi>Titchburne, Eſtwick,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall be a little in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, ſhall not a good part of the Army come into the City to guard the Parliament, keep the Works, put out the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does, ſuppreſſe tumults, and all to prevent a new Warre, and make an happie Peace?</p>
            <p n="16">16. Whether after the City have quitted their <hi>Militia,</hi> ſhall not <hi>London</hi> be the head quarter for Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax, Cromwell,</hi> and the other great Officers, the generall Rendezvous for all to come to? And whether muſt not the Aldermens Houſes, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114410:6"/>great Merchants and rich Tradeſmen be for quarter for them, their wives and children; and eſpecially for the great Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels, <hi>Huſon, Pride, Okey,</hi> &amp;c. who have no houſes of their own fit for their Honors to dwell in?</p>
            <p n="17">17. When <hi>London's Militia</hi> is in the power of the Army, who ſhall pay this meritorious glorious Army of Saints all their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, ſome behinde 50. weeks, ſome 30. weeks? And who ſhall maintain them for the time to come? ſhall not <hi>London</hi> be forced to it? and ſhall not whoever refuſes to pay the great ſummes laid upon them of thouſands and hundreds be plundered, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, judged Malignants, enemies to the Saints, that will not contribute to them who have ſaved the Kingdom from Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie; and by whoſe means alone they enjoy all they have?</p>
            <p n="18">18. When the Army hath poſſeſſion of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> whether or no may any Presbyterian or ill-affected perſon keep a ſword, gun, or any weapon in his houſe, for fear of <hi>raiſing a new war?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. Whether may any Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> whatever his ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſhall be, once dare to ſpeak a word againſt, or complain of the godly Army? And if they do, ſhall they not be tried by a Councell of War and the Gentlemen Agitators for their lives? can any thing leſſe then this be expected, ſeeing divers Sectaries here in <hi>London,</hi> before the Army hath the <hi>Militia,</hi> have threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned divers well affected perſons for but queſtioning ſome of the Armies proceedings, that they will complain to the Army of them; and that they ſhall be fetched away with a Troop of Horſe, and ſuch like.</p>
            <p n="20">20. Whether if once the Army have the Power of the <hi>Militia,</hi> of <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> ſhall not the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Common Councell be all put in by the Army, and all or moſt of the old ones be put out? And whether we muſt not have a Court of Aldermen and Common Councell all of the Armies Saints, and gifted Brethren, Alderman <hi>Staſemore</hi> the old Browniſt, Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Kiffin</hi> the yong Anabaptiſt, Alderman <hi>Clement Wrighter</hi> the Antiſcripturiſt, Alderman <hi>Overton</hi> the Seeker, Sir <hi>John, Lilbugne,</hi> Lord Mayor: and in caſe any prophane Presbyter ſhould be in that number, ſhall there not be a charge from the Army to put them out?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114410:7"/>
            <p n="21">21. Whether all the Demands of the Army hitherto both to Parliament and City, of not liſting, putting out Reformadoes, disbanding thoſe Companies that came from the Army, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting all the Forces of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> under oue Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, of the Cities <hi>Militia</hi> to be changed, with all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and proceedings of entertaining into their Army all ſorts, of ſeizing on Ammunition, of ſending of Agitators into all parts of the Kingdom to draw the Souldery, Navy, and all Countreys into combination with them, can tend to any thing elſe but the getting of all power into their hands, and leaving Kingdom, Parliament, City naked of all help; that ſo all lying at their mercy, and every mans head being on the block, they might either ſubmit to their conditions whatſoever they be, or elſe have their heads preſently chopt off.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Whether when the City hath parted with their <hi>Militia,</hi> and the Army be in poſſeſſion, how long ſhall the City enjoy their Orthodox Preachers; ſhall they not be quickly turned out, or elſe daily affronted in the diſcharge of their Miniſtery by every rude Souldier, and Mechanick, ſtanding up in the time of Preaching, Prayer, as they have done in other places, <hi>Bristow,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall they go quietly in the ſtreets for them? ſhall not every Pulpit be filled with Troopers, and all ſorts of ignorant Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks? and will not this City inſtead of ſound Doctrine, have all kinde of hereſie, blaſphemie, and error broached in Pulpits, and every ſtreet? Will not all the frogs and rabble of Sectaries from all parts of the Kingdom come up hither, and <hi>London</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the fink of all errors and confuſion? And ſhall they not all by the power of the Army have free quarter,<note place="margin">☞</note> and be maintained of the rich mens eſtates for preaching to them? O <hi>London,</hi> thy glory will depart from thee as ſoon as the Army hath thy <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia;</hi> and thou muſt bid adieu to the Goſpel, and thy faithfull Miniſters, Mr. <hi>Caelamie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cauton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Caſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="23">23. Whether for this laſt ſix weeks a Councell of War con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting for the moſt part of Officers, illeterate Mechanicks, and broken fortuned, and of Agitators common Troopers, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, hath not been the ſupreame Judicatory of this Kingdom, putting conditions and Laws on King, Parliament, City, and Kingdom? Nay whether have not King, Parliament, City and Kingdom been all true and honeſt Priſoners to the Army? And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114410:7"/>whether hath any thing been done in Parliament, or City, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe within theſe few dayes, but to confirm and execute the Votes and Acts of the Councell of War?</p>
            <p n="24">24. Whether or no this City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Magiſtrates thereof, have not juſt cauſe, when once their <hi>Militia</hi> is gone, and the Army hath power of the City, to expect their caſe and condition will be as the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> was when poſſeſſed by the Anabaptiſts, or rather worſe?<note place="margin">Read but the ſtory of the Anabaptiſts at Munſter as 'tis in Sleidan and as the Hiſtory of them was written in Engliſh in the firſt yeer of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Citizens will ſee what to truſt to, if ever this Army be Miſters of London.</note> Whether ſhall they not be ruled by Revelations? whether the great wicked men muſt not be turned out of all, that the Saints may inhabite the City? Whether will not Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> preach then as he hath done lately in the Army, that the beginning of Chriſts perſonall reign is come, and that he will put his Kingdom into the hands of his Saints? <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.18.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Whether can any wiſe underſtanding man, when the Army is poſſeſſed of the <hi>Militia</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and the Navy, but look for ſtrange things to be moved and acted, which yet they forbear out of Policy? Whether will they not then quite put down the Houſe of Peers according to the many books they have printed, and ſpeeches they have ſpoken to that purpoſe? Whether ſhall any Member of the Houſe of Commons, who is Presbyterian, and for the publick, ſit there any more? How long ſhall the Kings Majeſtie be uncharged, and unproceeded againſt by the Army, and the Houſe of Commons of their new modelling, what ſhall become of His royall Poſterity? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we not have Revelations of <hi>William Sedgwicks, Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſhes, Dells,</hi> that the day of Judgement to the wicked is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, and that new Jeruſalem the glorious ſtate of the Church is come, wherein <hi>Cromwell</hi> muſt be the King of Nations? And after this Army hath ſubdued all the wicked great Men, King, Nobles, Gentlemen, rich Citizens, &amp;c. then he muſt go with this Army to the gates of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and conquer the great <hi>Turk;</hi> and his Councell of State of 21. muſt be <hi>Lilburn, Overton, Heu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Paul Hobſon, Pride, Okey, Joyce,</hi> with ſo many of the Agitators as will fill up that number.</p>
            <p n="26">26. Whether doth this City of <hi>London</hi> yet ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fider and foreſee the infinite dangerous conſequences that muſt and will neceſſarily follow upon their giving up the <hi>Militia,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114410:8"/>what it is to be at the mercy and in the power of an Army, whoſe Commanders are generally men of mean parentage, breeding, eſtate; an Army not ruled by principles of war, their Generall and Commanders; but by Agitators choſen by the common Souldiers, and accountable to them: an Army that contrary to all their Oathes, Covenants, Proteſtations, have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed their truſt, and turned head againſt their Maſters; an Army that keeps to no principles nor rules, but their will and luſts; an Army whoſe principles for Religion, Civill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, libertie, propertie are prodigious, that change all their principles according to their fancies and advantages; an Army that hates this City to the death for their Remonſtrance, Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for Presbyteriall Government, change of the <hi>Militia,</hi> &amp;c. are theſe men fit to be truſted with the lives, eſtates, liberties of this City, yea of three Kingdoms? and they having gotten the power by tyrannie, force, and treacherie, will they not as Tyrants <hi>ſine Titulo,</hi> as guilty perſons and cowards, maintain their power by tyrannie, force, till they have taken all perſons and things out of the way they fear may do them hurt; will they not plead for all neceſſitie, ſelf preſervation, <hi>preventing of a new war,</hi> the peace of the Kingdom?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114410:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
